Alright,
we are on דף כג עמוד א, Daf Kaf-Gimel Amud Alef, but
we're going to start from eight lines from the top on כב
עמוד ב Kaf-Bet Amud Bet with אמר רב. Amar Rav.
And just to
bring
you back, we're talking about the סוגיא Sugya
of where
your wall can be relative to your neighbor's wall. How close it
can be, how far it needs to be.
The old מפרשים Mefarshim on the משנה, Mishnah, that was back on
כב עמוד א, Kaf-Bet Amud Alef, they talk about building this wall
in a לכתחילה Lechatchila situation where you're building some sort of perpendicular
wall
or there's already walls that exist and you're adding another wall. But
the גמרא, Gemara, as you saw with רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer yesterday,
is assuming that it's actually a case where one of the walls
fell down and now you're rebuilding the wall. So sometimes when walls
have just been up for a long time, no one knows who
was following the rules, whatever, but when you're rebuilding the wall, you
need to leave a certain distance. Do you know what that distance
is? ד' אמות. Dalet Amot.
Anyway, so we start with אמר רב לא שנו אלא כותל גינה
אבל כותל חצר אם בא
לסמוך סומך.
Amar Rav: Lo shanu ela kotel gina. Aval
kotel chatzer, im ba lismoch,
somech. So we're on כב עמוד ב, Kaf-Bet Amud Bet, eight lines
from the top, אמר רב. Amar Rav. So he says that oh,
this whole rule that the wall has to be ד' אמות Dalet
Amot away, that's in regards to the כותל kotel of
a garden, a גינה. gina. But the כותל kotel of a חצר,
chatzer, if you want to get it a little bit closer, you
can do it even closer than ד' אמות. Dalet Amot. What's the
distinction between the garden and a חצר? chatzer?
I'm up for participation here.
Does anybody have an interest? The walking and packing down of the
ground, I suppose. Yeah, exactly.
In a
גינה, gina, not as much things. In a חצר, chatzer, it's more
of a courtyard.
Yeah, exactly. So for the גינה, gina, which is like a garden
where things are being grown, there
since on one side of the wall no one is going to
be walking,
we want to create a space for people to be walking on
the other side because the walking helps people trample down the ground
and push it down, which like solidifies the foundation of the wall.
But in a חצר, chatzer, there's going to be people walking around
on the inside of the חצר, chatzer, which will pack down the
dirt around the area of the wall, and therefore we're not as
concerned with having this space on the other side of the wall
so that someone can walk between the two walls.
You know, I wonder why just packing down one side is going
to support the wall if the other side's not also packed down.
Yeah, I'm not sure how foundations for ancient walls work, but my
sense is that ground in general was maybe if the ground was
looser, that would be less good for the wall, and apparently just
walking around in one area would solidify it enough. Yeah, a totally
fair question. רבי אושעיא אומר אחד כותל גינה ואחד כותל חצר אם
בא לסמוך אין סומך.
Rabbi Oshia Omer: Echad kotel gina ve-echad kotel chatzer, im ba lismoch,
ein somech.
רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshia comes in and says actually, I don't buy
into this distinction of רב. Rav. And maybe this is for David's
reason.
Maybe, yeah, exactly, that's what I was thinking too.
For David's reason, saying like, okay, that's great that you're going to
pack down the foundation of one side of the wall, but what
about the other side of the wall?
The other side is not on your property, it doesn't affect the
other guy. You're only concerned with between your wall and his wall.
And therefore he needs to support your wall on your side.
Well, you built a wall. Right?
I imagine between your property and his property.
But there already is a wall.
So there's like a no-man's land in between that we're assuming he
has an interest in. But on the other side of the wall
is completely yours, I guess.
רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshia is saying you need to build your wall
with enough space between the two walls to walk on the outside
also, so that the ground is ostensibly packed down on both sides
for support securing.
Exactly. אמר רבי יוסי בר חנינא ולא פליגי. Amar Rabbi Yosi bar
Chanina: Velo pligi. So רבי יוסי בר חנינא Rabbi Yosi bar Chanina
says ולא פליגי, Velo pligi,
actually רב Rav and רבי אושעיא, Rabbi Oshia, they actually agree with
each other, they're just talking at two different scenarios. הא בעיר ישנה
הא בעיר חדשה. Ha be-ir yeshana, ha be-ir chadasha.
One of them, רבי אושעיא, Rabbi Oshia, is talking about a new
city, and רב Rav is talking about an old city. So difference
being that in an old city we assume that the ground is
already a little more packed down from being walked on for many
years or decades or whatever it is, but in a newly built
city we're going to have certain rules about the distance of the
walls in order to ensure the proper traffic and passage, passageway, in
order to get the city to a place where we feel like
it's sturdy. I sort of also feel like the distinction between an
old city and a new city is almost like in old cities
there's like less zoning laws, right? It's like a little more like
anything goes, this is the way people have been doing it. In
order to ensure the proper traffic and passageway in order to get
the city to a place where we feel like it's sturdy. I
sort of also feel like the distinction between old city and new
city is almost like in old cities there's like less zoning laws,
right? It's like a little more like anything goes. This is the
way people have been doing it, these little small alleyways and not
really not the wide streets. But in new cities when we get
to make it לכתחילה, l'chatchila, we're going to try to set up
the city in a way that's the most effective and the best
for creating a functional and sturdy sturdy city. Now from the משנה:
mishna: החלונות בין מלמעלה בין מלמטה בין מכנגדן ארבע אמות. hachalonot bein
milmala bein milmata bein miknegdan arba amot.
So we had in our משנה mishna we saw before that let's
say
there's
windows on your neighbor's property. So Michal and I live next door
to each other. Michal has a window and now I'm coming to
build a wall that's going to be across from her window.
So we said that what?
It's like in February talk about taking away some of these views.
Yeah and usually you can't do anything about it.
So I think you're less concerned about the view and the situation
and more concerned about other people looking in,
which is
now
we have curtains so it's not as much of an issue. But
so we say so how does this work? So Michal has her
window and now I'm coming to build a wall. We said that
the top of my wall, i.e., my wall either needs to be
ארבע אמות arba amot high, eight feet taller than Michal's window than
the top of Michal's window or eight feet ארבע אמות arba amot
below
and at least ארבע אמות arba amot away. So why is ארבע
אמות arba amot above? So ותני עלה v'tani ala we have in
a ברייתא: braita: מלמעלה כדי שלא יציץ ויראה. milmala k'dei shelo yatzitz
v'yireh.
So it needs to go ארבע אמות arba amot above in order
so that I don't like coming on my wall and like bend
down and like peek in, right? If I climb up on my
wall and I'm sitting there and I'm bending over and looking in,
so if the wall is high enough, like I'm not, there's no
human being that's eight feet tall that could really ever lean down
to the extent that they'd be able to see in. מלמטה שלא
יעמוד ויראה milmata shelo yaamod v'yireh
this one is a bit more likely that
if I have a small wall it needs to be at least
eight feet below so that way if I'm standing on the window
I won't be able to like I won't be able to peek
in. So these ארבע אמות arba amot in both these situations represents
the height more than the height of a human being is the
way I had understood this measurement, which I think is interesting to
think about like we usually think of ארבע אמות arba amot as
the area around a human being, like the width of a human
being, like what is my ארבע אמות arba amot what is my
private space?
And here ארבע אמות arba amot is actually signifying in some way
the ארבע אמות arba amot around the window but it seems a
little bit connected to the height of a person which
is about six
eight feet, yeah, which I
never I never thought about before that the private space width is
somehow connected where it's somehow yeah somehow connected to people human being's
height.
It matches the fact that your arm your arm span is roughly
equal to your height.
Oh that's very interesting too. Right so if I'm if yeah so
like when we're exercising in gym class and they tell you like
stretch out it's always like make sure you can do jumping jacks
and you aren't going to bump into anyone which is literally making
ארבע אמות arba amot circles around yourself but
I never thought about that before.
All right this coffee is great, thank you.
You're welcome. ומכנגדן umiknegdan and the wall opposite שלא יאפיל shelo yaafil
in order that it shouldn't be make the you shouldn't cause any
darkness. We don't want to so as opposed to a view where
this is more concerned about natural light and if your wall is
too close to the window you're going to block the influx of
natural light into the other person's house whereas if you're far enough
the sun can still shine in.
So now the גמרא gemara says the
גמרא gemara has a question. The ברייתא braita just gave a reason
why your wall has to be ארבע אמות. arba amot. What was
the reason the ברייתא braita just said? In order so that you
shouldn't cause too much darkness in your friend in your neighbor's house.
But didn't the גמרא gemara just give a different reason in our
משנה mishna for why it has to be ארבע אמות? arba amot?
So the גמרא gemara asks that. So טעמא שלא יאפיל אבל משום
דבשא לא. tama shelo yaafil aval mishum d'vasha lo.
Is that how you pronounce it? דבשא? d'vasha? דבשא? d'vasha?
אבל
משום דבשא לא
aval
mishum
d'vasha lo but the reason that the ברייתא braita didn't give they
didn't talk about the trampling and the packing down. So הכא במאי
עסקינן hacha b'mai askinan so what are we dealing with? בבא מן
הצד b'va min hatzad
where you're building the wall perpendicular to it. So this is a
situation where Michal has her wall with her windows and if you
don't want me to use your name as an example I won't.
You have your wall with your windows and I come and I
build a wall perpendicular to it so making an L-shape. So there
it's not necessarily a question of walking by because
people
won't be walking by that way anymore per se and it's really
a question about... How close can my wall be, if this is
the wall, here's the window, how close can my wall be up
to her window or will it still cast too much of a
shadow?
Blocking the walls with windows,
דפשתא. dafshta. But that was discussing the walls without windows, my mind.
I don't see why
they couldn't have answered that here. Yeah, if this is a case
of דפשתא, dafshta, the reason that was given, that reason, I think
it was a question of
why would you even need the window reason if you already have
דפשתא? dafshta? Why would, meaning
the גמרא Gemara is trying to understand what is the reason in
our משנה. Mishna. Or are you saying so the משנה Mishna is
just dealing with a case where there wasn't windows?
Whatever case it was, what we were discussing before, that when they
brought that reason, I think it was a case of saying why
do you need to bring a second reason if you have the
first too?
Yeah, meaning in the ברייתא. Braita. So either there's a question on
the משנה Mishna or it's a question on the ברייתא. Braita. Great.
But now we've created another scenario. So that was one interesting way
of מחלק, mechalek, another here way is that saying that one of
the walls is perpendicular.
The כמה. kama. So I thought this, this is like definitely a,
so the question is how far away from the window does it
have to be when in a situation of a perpendicular wall? How
far from the window does it have to be? I think this
is a great example of the גמרא Gemara either picking an אמורא
Amora or changing his name or something. אמר ייבא חמוה דאשין בר
נדבך. Amar Yiva chamueh d'Ashin bar Nidbach. But like the,
there’s literally like when the wall comes to be trampled.
Like if you look at the Hebrew word, it's like a clear
pun on all the phrase, on the concepts of our גמרא, Gemara,
which is a funny thing the גמרא Gemara does sometimes.
משמיה דרב, Mishmei de-Rav, כמלא רוחב חלון. kemlo rochav chalon. So the
wall needs to be, oh, a window's width away. So if Michal
has a four-foot wide window, presumably my wall needs to be another
four feet, my perpendicular wall needs to be another four feet
away
from where your window is.
והא לא מצית, veha lo metzit, but then the person's gonna just
look in. Right? It's so close, like even if it's high enough,
I'll be able to just peek in. Right? When if the wall
is close enough and you got the right angle, you're just gonna
see right into the house. אמר רב זביד במדרית כותלו. Amar Rav
Zevid bemadrit kotlo.
So he says no, what he did, what we say is that
the situation is the wall, he curved it at the top. He
created an incline at the top of the wall that he wouldn't
be able to climb up on top of it. Right?
So you've seen these kinds of walls before where they will put
some sort of curvature on the top and it creates a better
security system because, and in this situation, it creates, you're not gonna
have the same situation of היזק ראיה, hezek re'iyah, you're not gonna
be able to see in because a person's gonna have a hard
time climbing up because it's not a flat top, it's a curved,
a curved top.
Some places they put glass, you know, for
security, cut glass
into the cement.
Oh right, right, right,
or barbed wire.
אמר רב זביד במדרית כותלו. Amar Rav Zevid bemadrit kotlo. והנן תנן
ארבע אמות. Ve-hanan tenan arba amot. Wait, now you're telling me it's
the width of the window,
but we already had a measurement, shouldn't it be ארבע אמות? arba
amot? תני לא קשיא כאן ברוח אחת כאן בשתי רוחות.
Tanei lo kashya kan beruach achat
kan bishtei ruchot.
You need to do ארבע אמות arba amot when there's just one
wall. But when you have two walls, let's say so Michal has
her property with her window and I'm building two walls which sort
of almost creates a passageway right directly to her window, then that's
where we're going to determine the other width.
It's not going to be the ד אמות, dalet amot, it's going
to be just the width of the windows.
In
that direction?
From one direction versus two directions?
The way I understood was
so it's narrower when you're putting two walls?
So it would be the opposite.
So if you have one wall, then you're gonna get the one
window's width away, and if you have two walls, then we're gonna
create, then
you think of like a 12-foot passage, it's not going to be
particularly narrow?
12 feet is, ארבע אמות arba amot is, no
but is it ארבע אמות
arba amot between the walls or is it ארבע אמות, arba amot,
no, it's gonna be ארבע אמות arba amot between the edge of
the window and the wall on either side. So you're gonna wind
up with like at least eight אמות amot wide passage.
And there's a contradiction between the language of
מלא רוחב חלון melo rochav chalon and ארבע אמות? arba amot? Yeah.
Okay.
תא שמע. Ta shema. והכותל מן המזקילה ארבע אמות Ve-ha-koteil min ha-mazkila
arba amot כדי שיזקיף את הסולם. kedei she-yazkif et ha-sulam. So actually,
they anticipate our next משנה Mishna here.
The next משנה Mishna that we're going to see in two minutes
talks about, let's say a person has a gutter on their wall,
on top of their wall. So somebody else's building is building another
wall across from it, he has to do at least four אמות
amot in order so that the person with the gutter can put
up a ladder to fix to fix their gutter. So the גמרא's
Gemara going to ask the same question we asked before: Wait, is
the reason because we want to give space for a ladder or
is the reason this issue of the trampling and packing down the
earth? טעמא משום סולם אבל משום דפשא לא. Taama mishum sulam aval
mishum davsha lo. הכא במאי עסקינן Hacha bemai askinan במזחילה משופעת bemazchila
meshupaat דאי משום דפשא הא קאזיל ואתי תותיה. dei mishum davsha ha
kaazil vaati tutei.
So that we're dealing with a situation where the gutter is on
some sort of overhang.
The gutter is on an overhang and therefore there's not going to
be an issue of דפשא davsha because a person could walk underneath
the gutter.
But since the new wall is going to be four אמות amot
from the overhang. So that... does that make sense to people?
Yeah? Okay, should I draw it or we're good? Yeah? So since
there's an overhang, there's not going to be an issue of trampling
because a person can walk underneath and still be trampling and we're
not the distance of the new wall is not going to affect
trampling, but it is going to still need to take into account
the ability of the owner to put a ladder to fix his
gutter. Okay. משנה: Mishna: מרחיקין את הסולם מן השובך ארבע אמות כדי
שלא תקפוץ הנמייה Marchikin et hasulam min hashovach arba amot kedei shelo
tikpotz hanemiya ואת הכותל
מן המזחילה ארבע אמות כדי שיהיה זוקף את הסולם.
veet hakotel min hamazchila arba
amot kedei sheyehei zokef et hasulam. So the first case is that
let's say there's a wall between my property and Michal's property and
Michal is raising pigeons, she has a שובך shovach or a dovecote
and
I'm
putting up a ladder to do whatever it is I need to
do, I need to put my ladder at least four אמות amot
away from the dovecote. We're not talking about the distance from the
dovecote to the wall, but rather if Michal's שובך shovach is
over
here and I have a wall here, so I'd have to put
my my ladder right here as opposed to right here because if
you put it right in the middle right across from the dovecote,
what's going to be the issue? We're afraid that this weasel or
mongoose-type thing is going to climb up the ladder and jump down
and eat all the pigeons whereas if I put the ladder a
little bit farther away, it's not going to jump in the same
extent.
You have a gutter system, so this whole thing, I'm not... the
gutter system.
You have a whole gutter system, I'm sorry I'm going backwards. It's
okay. רש''י Rashi explains the whole thing.
Yeah it really sounds...
it just sounds like our gutter system.
It's like exactly the same.
Yeah. רש''י's Rashi's like you gotta get the ladder to get all
the... yeah. Okay, ואת הכותל מן
המזחילה
ארבע אמות כדי שיהיה זוקף את הסולם.
veet hakotel min hamazchila arba amot kedei
sheyehei
zokef et hasulam.
So this is what we saw before, that the distance from the
gutter also needs the wall distance from the gutter needs to be
four אמות. amot. לימא מתניתין דלא כרבי יוסי? Lima matnitin dila ke-Rabbi
Yosi? Let's say that our משנה mishna is not like רבי יוסי,
Rabbi Yosi, why? דאי רבי יוסי, Dei i Rabbi Yosi, if it's
רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, הא אמר: ha amar: זה חופר בתוך שלו
וזה נוטע בתוך שלו. zeh chofer betoch shelo vezeh noteiah betoch shelo.
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi was of the position that I have my
property and you have your property, I get to do whatever I
want on my property and you get to do whatever you want
on your property and I don't need to worry about how I
affect you. רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yosi was sort of like... what's mine is mine, what's
yours is yours, like friendly neighbors, like we each get to do
what we get to do, that's what that's like the benefit of
having your own property is you get to do what you want
on it.
So one guy could be digging holes, the other guy could be
digging trees, and the guy who lives next door can't be like,
well you can't, don't dig a hole now because you're going to
ruin my... like no, this is my property, that's your property, don't
worry about it.
So if you say רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, so even if you
could even say that our משנה mishna is... so why is that
not sound like why can our משנה mishna not be like רבי
יוסי? Rabbi Yosi? Because our משנה mishna was saying like be sensitive,
don't put your ladder too close, make sure your wall is far
enough from the gutter.
And רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yosi like, yeah, you don't have to be
sensitive at all. So if you say רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, even
if you could even say that our משנה mishna is like רבי
יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, האמר רב אשי: ha amar Rav Ashi: כי הוינא
בי רב כהנא הוה אמר: ki havina bei Rav Kahana hava amar:
מודה רבי יוסי בגירי דידיה. modeh Rabbi Yosi begirei dideh. הכא נמי
זימנין דבהדי דמנח ליה יתבא בחור וקפצה.
Hacha nami zimnin debehadi
demanach lei yatva bechor vekaptza.
So we say, no רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, that's true that like
generally you don't have to be sensitive, but if you're shooting arrows,
if you're shooting arrows at the other guy's property, that's that's
that's crossed the line.
If you're shooting arrows, that's going to be a problem. And we're
saying like here, like we know that weasels live in holes and
wait for ladders to be put up so they can run up
and get the pigeons and that is way that is like way
too much of a direct affront to your neighbor's property. So we
say... what? וגרמא
הוא? Vegrama hu? And this is... this is not a case of
גרמא? germa? Like... wait, it's one thing if I'm shooting arrows into
the other guy's property, like all I'm doing is putting up a
ladder. The fact that a weasel or a mongoose, whatever it is,
is climbing out of a hole, jumping up and then attacking it,
like... That, that's גרמא. grama. גרמא Grama is our—is the term for
indirect indirect damage.
Hopefully we've seen it by now on כ"ב, chaf bes, בבא בתרא.
Bava Basra. It dealt with גרמא. grama.
Are you familiar, right?
Yeah. Okay. So אמר רב טובי בר מתנא זאת אומרת גרמא בנזיקין
אסור. Amar Rav Tuvi bar Matna zot omeret grama b'nezikin asur. So
actually this is coming to say that גרמא בנזיקין grama b'nezikin is
אסור, asur, that you can't do something that causes indirect damage. רב
יוסף הוה ליה הני תלאי דהוו אתו אמני ויתבי תותייהו ואתו עורבי
אכלי דמא וסלקי
אדי תלאי
ומפסדי תמרי.
Rav Yosef hava lei haneletale d'havu atu umnei v'yasve
tuteihu v'atu orve achli dama v'silki
adei talei u'mafsdei tamrei. So רב יוסף Rav Yosef had these date
trees,
and the—what used to happen was these bloodletters
used to come and sit under—this was like a nice place to
sit, they would come and sit under the trees and they would
do their bloodletting, and all of this blood that they would just
like leave on the ground would attract ravens who would come to
eat the blood and then they would also fly up into the
trees and ruin the dates.
So אמר להו רב יוסף אפיקו לי קורקורמי
מהכא.
Amar lehu Rav Yosef
afiku li kurkurmei mehacha. He says get—get out of here, get the
crows away from here! Like you need to—you guys need to get
out from under this tree. So אמר ליה אביי והא גרמא הוא?
Amar leh Abaye v'ha grama hu? אביי Abaye is like, wait, is
this not a case of גרמא? grama? Like you're mad at the
bloodletters who are coming there and sitting and doing their bloodletting and
then the ravens are coming—like that's not their fault. This is like
way many steps down the road, down the line from the action
that they're doing. They're not causing damage to רב יוסף's Rav Yosef
trees. So אמר ליה הכי אמר רב טובי בר מתנא זאת אומרת
גרמא בנזיקין אסור. Amar leh hachi amar Rav Tuvi bar Matna zot
omeret grama b'nezikin asur. So as opposed to—as opposed to saying like,
no, this is not גרמא, grama, like yeah it is a גרמא,
grama, and גרמא grama is אסור. asur. Not cool.
Prohibited.
והא אחזיקו להו? V'ha ichzaku lehu? But הם אחזיקו להו? v'ha chazaka?
But they've like been coming and sitting here for decades. This is
like our spot. Everyone knows when you need some bloodletting done you
come to the guy sitting under the trees. Like they have a
חזקה. chazaka. So אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה אין
חזקה לנזיקין. Amar Rav Nachman amar Rabba bar Avuha ein chazaka l'nezikin.
No, no, no, you don't get to claim that like oh I've
been doing this forever, I have a חזקה, chazaka, I have like
an established
situation here if you're causing
נזיקין. nezikin. Right?
Because that goes against what we were saying earlier in the זכות?
zechut? That there was—what was it?
It was like if someone's—it was like if someone's venting and they've
been doing something for however long you can't stop them and it
seemed like a נזיקין nezikin type of case. Like your smoke is
blowing into their house
as an example.
Or just the upstairs, the warehouses. Yeah. Like if the warehouse is
on the second floor,
if the warehouse was there first, then but it
makes things smell
and
then it would be a problem but if the warehouse wasn't there
first then you wouldn't be able to stop them
from—I understand.
So
the גמרא—so Gemara where were they sitting?
It sounds like they're sitting in public property.
So what do we say? איתמר עלה רב מרי. Inmar la Rav
Mari. So I think רב מרי Rav Mari actually deals with exactly
you guys' question. They're like wait, אין חזקה לנזיקין? ein chazaka l'nezikin?
Like are you sure? איתמר עלה, Inmar la, let's qualify it.
איתמר עלה רב מרי אמר בקוטרא
ורב זביד אמר בבית הכסא.
Inmar la Rav Mari amar
b'kutra v'Rav Zevid amar b'veit hachisei. So we say wait, when we
say אין חזקה לנזיקין, ein chazaka l'nezikin, that's like really bad things
where there's like a lot of smoke coming in,
or when there's a—when there's a bathroom nearby, like an owner can
say like okay, there might have been a bathroom there but like
this is disgusting, like I don't want this near my house or
whatever the smoke process is—like this is not okay being near my
property and he can—he can change it. So then רב יוסף Rav
Yosef comes, so we say אמר להו הני לדידי דאנינא דעתי כקוטרא
וכבית הכסא דמי לי. Amar lehu hani l'didi d'anina da'ati k'kutra u'veit
hachisei damyan li. Actually these ravens flying into my—into my trees, that's
like כאילו ke'ilu there's a bathroom right here. That's like כאילו ke'ilu
there's smoke coming in. So what's really interesting here is that we've
taken some sort of like objective measure about like נזיקין, nezikin, חזקה
chazaka for נזיקין, nezikin, and we've said like רב יוסף Rav Yosef
is able to just claim like hey I'm actually in fact very
sensitive to this. And there's like a מחלוקת—is machloket he sensitive to
the fact that the ravens are coming to eat his dates? Is
he sensitive maybe—sensitive to the blood from the bloodletting itself? That he's
trying to—he's trying to get out of?
Because that's interesting. In other words,
eating the dates off of the tree is like a real נזק.
nezek. On the other hand, it's not—in other words I'm not saying
that's nothing disgusting, it's a real נזק, nezek, but it's subjective.
Right, but eating the
dates—I find that disgusting but these birds are eating my dates. So
it's—but it's a little leap that's being made right?
Yeah, I
mean it's not just the birds, it's the birds are, you know,
any type—so it's sort of indirect because the bloodletting is
separate
from
the birds—it's not like he sent the
birds over to do the
נזק.
nezek. Okay.
You buy a property and I sit outside your property in public
and I feed the pigeons, I throw seeds on the ground, and
8,000
pigeons, you're a pigeon man, and
their stuff is now all over your yard. Exactly. And I'm sitting
in the park, it's public space. Right. Yeah, that seems to be
the dispute.
It does, but you wonder it's like רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, like
you bought this property next to the Central Park, you know there's
going to be pigeon men there who are feeding the pigeons.
Exactly, you made a choice.
You made a choice, right? The claim here is well, these bloodletters
have been coming for years. Well, when you buy a property, that's
like part of the research you do. But it's sort of an
argument on back and yet the גמרא Gemara seems to honor רב
יוסף'ס Rav Yosef's subjective sensitivity to this, which is very fascinating. And
I think what makes me think that it's more about thinking that
the birds are disgusting is because it's like לדידי דאנינא דעתי ככשורא
בי קניא דמיא ליה. lididi d'anina daati kikushra bei kanya damya lei.
Like it's not the claim isn't like, yeah but they're actually legitimately
damaging my dates.
The claim is like in my opinion it's
like a bad smell of a bathroom or like smoke coming in.
Like a bathroom, yeah.
All right, we're going to keep plowing ahead here so we can
catch up. מרחיקין את השובך מן העיר חמישים אמה. merachikin et hashovach
min hair chamishim ama. Sorry, just
so now we got really excited about dovecotes and so now we're
going to talk about doves and how far doves can fly and
when you find doves that are we're going to start talking about
finding doves and it's going to be exciting for the next thirty
minutes. מרחיקין את השובך מן העיר, merachikin et hashovach min hair, so
if I'm starting a dovecote I have to move it at least
fifty אמות amot from the city. ולא יעשה אדם שובך בתוך שלו
אלא אם כן יש לו חמישים אמה לכל
רוח. velo yaaseh adam shovach betoch shelo ela im ken yesh lo
chamishim ama lachol ruach. And a person can't build a dovecote in
his own property unless he has a fifty אמות amot circumference that
can go around the dovecote. It's interesting just parallel to what we
were talking about before the ד' אמות daled amot of a person,
here now we're saying that the dove the personal space of doves
or the property space of doves is this fifty אמות amot distance.
אלא אם כן יש לו לכל
רוח. ela im ken yesh
lo lachol ruach. רבי יהודה אומר בית ארבע כורין מלא שגר היונה.
Rabbi Yehuda omer beit arba korin melo shegar hayona. ואם
לקחה
אפילו
בית רובע
הרי הוא בחזקתו.
ve-im lekacha afilu beit rova
harei hu be-chezkato. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda actually has a different
distance, he says בית ארבע כורין beit arba korin which is a
lot bigger than the hundred than the fifty אמות amot circumference.
273? 273 אמות amot circumference.
אמות amot is what it comes to.
Yeah, so it's like pretty far and he says that's the distance
that a bird, we say מלא שגר היונה, melo shegar hayona, it's
the distance that a bird can fly sort of in one in
one go. ואם לקחה אפילו בית רובע הרי הוא
בחזקתו. ve-im lekacha afilu beit rova harei hu be-chezkato. But let's say
I bought a property and there was already a dovecote on the
property and this dovecote was on the property and it was actually
kind of small or not so far away from the borders, because
there's a חזקה chazaka
it's permitted and the assumption is that like I had already talked
to the surrounding neighbors or the previous owner had sort of already
gotten an okay for where this dovecote was.
גמרא Gemara says חמישים
אמה חמישים אמה ותו לא ורמינהי אין פורסין נשבין ליונה אלא אם
כן היה רחוק
מן הישוב שלשים
ריס.
hamishim ama hamishim ama v'tu lo u'remini ein porsin nishbin leyona
ela im ken haya rachok min hayishuv
sheloshim ris.
So the גמרא Gemara says
you can't set out
traps, you can't set out dove traps from
in near in like the city or in near the property unless
it's
שלשים ריס, sheloshim ris, thirty ריס ris
from the settlement area. So if I want to capture pigeon doves
and I want to set up traps for them, I can't do
it like really close to the city because what am I going
to wind up doing? I'm just going to wind up trapping all
the doves that already belong to people.
אמר אביי משיתי טובא וכחשי בחמישים אמתא מליא. amar Abaye mishiti tuva
ve-chasheu be-chamishim amata milia. So אביי'ס Abaye's like yeah, it's true that
theoretically if you're doing that you have to fly set up your
traps really far, but in terms of like how far a dove
is going to travel by the time it travels fifty אמות amot
it's already like eaten along the way and slowed down and it's
sort of going to fifty אמות amot is going to be the
extent to which we're sensitive to this other person's doves, we think
that fifty אמות amot is when the bird is going to slow
down.
Suddenly say
what?
They don't eat out.
Yeah, they don't eat they don't eat past that. So I guess
a person could set up yeah,
especially if it's especially if it's meat. If it's dairy then maybe
they
they wouldn't. The guy's setting up a trap farther away and the
bird's like I don't want cheese or like I don't want more
crackers like I've already eaten like fifty אמות amot worth of crackers
on my way out of here. So משלושים ריסין mishloshim risin is
that is that how far they could fly? ותו לא vetu lo
and not more? ותניא vatanya ובישוב אפילו מאה מיל לא
יפרוס uvishuv afilu me'ah mil lo yifros then that we have another
ברייתא braisa that says you can't set up even within a hundred
מיל. mil. רב יוסף אמר Rav Yosef amar בישוב
כרמים.
bishuv
kramim. רב יוסף Rav Yosef said no that's dealing with the situation
of the settlement of vineyards.
And the idea being that
I know
so I think that
because there's these vineyard set up they can actually fly further distances.
I think that with the I my what רש״י Rashi says is
כרמים שפורחים מכרם לכרם ושתים מרבי. kramim sheporchin mikeren lekeren veshatin marbe.
It sounds like they fly further as a result of these vineyards
and it could be the idea that when there's vineyards I don't
know if they eat grapes but maybe there's less for them to
eat because you have all this like plantation with all this vineyard
land and there's less for them to eat and they would just
wind up keep on flying further or they just have some ability
to rest I'm not sure exactly what it is but the idea
is that they can go farther.
רבא אמר Rava amar בישוב שובכין. bishuv shovchin. And רבא Rava is
like no no no why do you have to
make it really far away? Because it's in the ישוב yishuv of
שובך. shovach. This is like this is like a dove-cote settlement and
everyone's got dove-cotes and there's just like birds everywhere so you gotta
build you gotta go really far away.
Yeah because the
and also because these doves are just hopping from dove-cote to dove-cote
and they can just go for miles. So
ותיבעי ליה משום
שובכין
גופייהו
vetibaga'ei mishum shovchin
gufaihu
and why to say like you don't even need
ותיבעי ליה משום
שובכין
גופייהו
vetibaga'ei mishum shovchin
gufaihu
or just say that it's actually a case of his own שובך.
shovach. איבעית אימא דידי ibayis ayma didei ואיבעית אימא דעכו"ם ve'ibayis ayma
d'akumni ואיבעית אימא דהפקר. ve'ibayis ayma dehefker. So who
the גמרא Gemara deals with what who are all what are all
these other שובך? shovach? So some say that it could be their
own שובך shovachs so it doesn't
matter you set up the trap it doesn't matter because he's going
to be all these anyway.
Exactly. Or either they're all his שובך shovachs or they belong to
גויים goyim and we don't or so we don't care or these
are just some random dove-cotes that have been set up and then
we don't care and therefore we say that it's okay to set
it up in a closer distance.
Oh very good very neighborly.
Yeah terrible. Love the Jews.
רבי יהודה אומר
Rabbi Yehuda omer
בית ארבע כורין
וכולי.
beis arba
korin vechula. אמר רב פפא ואיתימא רב זביד amar Rav Papa v'iseyma
Rav Zavid זאת אומרת טוענין ללוקח וטוענין ליורש. zos omeres to'anin lalo'ke'ach
veto'anin layoresh.
So the implication of the last line where we say about אם
לקח אפילו בית רובע הרי הוא בחזקתו im lachach afilu beis rova
harei hu bechezkaso
that seems to imply that sorry גמרא Gemara says אמר רב פפא
ואיתימא רב זביד amar Rav Papa v'iseyma Rav Zavid זאת אומרת טוענין
ללוקח וטוענין
ליורש
zos omeres to'anin lalo'ke'ach
veto'anin layoresh the בית דין Beis Din is willing to make claims
for somebody who purchases and for somebody who inherits. That the situation
is that let's say somebody else comes and makes a claim against
you so if you've been a recent purchaser or a recent inheritor
the בית דין Beis Din sort of already has a built-in claim
for you that you don't necessarily have to like bring evidence the
בית דין Beis Din can sort of rely on some sort of
a חזקה. chazaka. So
יורש תנינא לה yoresh tanina lo wait what are you you're going
to extrapolate from our משנה Mishnah about a יורש? yoresh? We already
learned the יורש yoresh explicitly in a different משנה. Mishnah. הבא משום
ירושה אינו צריך טענה haba mishum yerusha eino tzarich ta'ana somebody who
comes brings a claim against somebody who's an inheritor he doesn't need
to have a claim going for him.
לוקח איצטריכא ליה loke'ach itztarichlei no so we need the חידוש chiddush
of רב פפא Rav Papa and רב זביד Rav Zavid is that
regarding a buyer that his חזקה chazaka is sort of already established
his claim is already established by a בית דין. Beis Din. So
לוקח נמי תנינא loke'ach nami tanina but we have a משנה Mishnah
about לוקח loke'ach as well. לקח חצר ובה זיזין וגזוזטראות loke'ach chatzer
uva zizin uguztra'os you buy if you bought a courtyard and there
was different protrusions and balconies sticking out into the public sphere הרי
זה בחזקתו. harei zeh bechezkaso.
So we already have another משנה Mishnah itself where we already said
like so don't tell me that our משנה Mishnah is coming to
teach us about a חזקה chazaka for a יורש yoresh and a
לוקח loke'ach like we already have other explicit משניות mishnayos about that
we wouldn't be needing to extrapolate that from our case here that
if you buy a שובך shovach that's within a certain space that
that חזקה chazaka or that claim is already built in from בית
דין. Beis Din. So it says no צריכא tzericha we actually need.
We need, we need it for both.
דאשמעינן התם גבי רשות הרבים דאימור כונס לתוך שלו
הוא
De-ashmi'inan hatam gabei reshut harabbim
de-imor konas letoch shelo hu אינמי אחולי אחלו בני רשות
הרבים גביה. inami achuli achlu bnei reshut harabbim gabeih. So if we
would have only taught about the לקוח, lokayach,
we would have thought that that's special for the לקוח lokayach because
the stuff goes next to the רשות הרבים reshut harabbim and maybe
he got permission from the public sphere or they either like they
literally granted permission or they're like, "Yeah, we know that this is
like coming into the public sphere but like we forgive it."
But here when we're just we're dealing with private properties, no. או
השמעינן הכא Ou hashmi'inan hacha or if we would have just only
taught about the private situation, כיון דיחיד הוא אימא פיוסי פייסיה. kevan
de-yachid hu eima payesei payeseih. Maybe like the guy, the owner, he
talked to the surrounding people and he like made some sort of
deal with them. He's like, "Listen, my birds are gonna probably poop
a little bit on your stuff or eat a little bit, but
like I'm gonna compensate you for that."
אינמי אחולי אחלו Inami achuli achlu or they're like, "Nah, don't worry
about it. It's cool. We're okay with the pigeons around." גבי ברבים
מאן פייס Gabei berabbim man payis but like like what? Your person's
going to make a get appease who who's the public person that
he's going to like, "Alright, anybody who walks by gets to take
a dollar," for for how is he striking up that deal?
ומאן שביק עמיה לא אימא לא צריכא
U-man shavik imei lo eima
lo tzricha and who's going to take it, right? Who's he going
to make a deal with and who's going to or who's he
interacting with? The public? Like how is that helpful to us? So
we say no, so it's צריכא tzricha therefore we need to extrapolate
both.
Okay, הרי הוא בחזקתו. harei hu bechezkat-o. והאמר רב נחמן אמר רבה
בר אבוה אין חזקה לניזקין. Ve-ha amar Rav Nachman amar Rabba bar
Avuha ein chazakah lenezekin. So say, "Oh look,
the fact is you have the חזקה chazakah on this dovecote and
we see that אין חזקה לניזקין." ein chazakah lenezekin. So רב מרי
אמר בכותרא רב זביד אמר בבית הכסא. Rav Mari amar bekutra Rav
Zavid amar beveit hakissei. And here we have the qualification again that
when we say אין חזקה לניזקין ein chazakah lenezekin that's specifically for
really putrid smelling situations.
Wait, so does אין חזקה לניזקין ein chazakah lenezekin here mean
that
what?
That here we see,
I think we're extrapolating the fact that
I think it's it's all it's the whole statement together. אין חזקה
לניזקין רב מרי אמר בכותרא רב זביד אמר בבית הכסא Ein chazakah
lenezekin Rav Mari amar bekutra Rav Zavid amar beveit hakissei and this
is coming as another example here that אין חזקה לניזקין ein chazakah
lenezekin is limited to those situations, which is why in our case
in the משנה Mishnah we allow for the היזק hezek to occur.
We say like, "Yeah, there might be some היזק hezek by these
dovecotes, but that's
that's a חזקה chazakah that is permitted." And the times we say
אין חזקה לניזקין ein chazakah lenezekin
not all theoretical sources of נזק nezek are equal.
Yeah, some we're going to allow and some we're going to allow
and some we're not going to allow. Yeah.
I think in all these situations these are all like indirect נזיקין.
nezikin. Yeah, right. The idea of a smell is different than like
right if like a guy if a guy if I buy a
property and like the next morning I wake up and my neighbor's
over like just like chopping at my trees and I'm like, "Hey
dude, what are you doing? You're damaging my trees." He's like, "No,
no, no, I've always been doing this." Like there's no הוה אמינא
hava amina that that would be okay. So this אין חזקה לניזקין
ein chazakah lenezekin is like דווקא davka in this situation, in this
like more middle ground situation. And here we're dealing with smells, but
I could see a similar view for poop, the you know the
smell of bird poop or them eating at things, or maybe noise
would be another modern example, right? Like you move next door and
the people are like, "Oh, we've had a band practice here for
the last
15 years."
Like you moved onto Abbey Road, like you don't get to
you don't get to be like, "Well, why is there Beatles music
all the time?"
Like in the case of a גזוסטרא, gezustra, like there's an overhang,
like the house is like by the רשות הרבים. reshut harabbim. So
some but so the case is what? Somebody lived in that house
for 50 years and they died and now it's a ירושה. yerusha.
At that moment people could start making a טענה. ta'anah.
Yeah, they're like, "Yeah, what's the deal why your balcony hanging over?"
Even though like they were waiting for the guy who was living
in there to die, now a new person moved in
and they're gonna so we say that the בית דין Beit Din
already builds in the claim. No, no, it's it's like grandfathered in.
Grandfathered. Yeah.
And what about the thoughts that we sort of did say what
we said right before the משנה Mishnah that, you know, for me
this is like
a subjective דעת da'at house.
What for a balcony over a public space?
Yeah, well anything, yeah, I mean what's right
why do we sometimes give in to this person's like subjective subjective
sensibilities?
So I'm curious, so I think if you had your balcony over
your neighbor's property and you were smoking, right, that would be a
different thing. But here it sounds like the balcony situation is like
over this like public space and it sort of sounds like
it's yeah, it's a public space, you can't apply the the subjective
thing, right?
Like I walked on... If I walk down the street I can't
be like, oh this guy, this guy's got a chicken coop and
this guy's doing this and this guy is playing loud music, it's
like, yeah, you're in the street, that's something you're gonna have to
deal with, the private properties that surround it and the things, the
smells and sounds that are coming out of it.
Or other protrusions. Great.
We have fifteen minutes and we have a small little עמוד. amud.
So we got it. All right. ניפול הנמצא בתוך חמישים אמה. Nippul
hanimsa betoch chamishim ama. So now we're dealing with the dove chick.
Okay. This is like a baby dove that does not yet know
how to fly.
So we call it a ניפול. nippul. It seems like it fell,
maybe גוזל. gozal. Yeah, גוזל. gozal. Yeah.
Maybe it was hanging on to a bigger dove and it fell
or or maybe it walked out, the term is ניפול. nippul. Yeah.
ניפול הנמצא בתוך
חמישים אמה הרי הוא של בעל השובך.
Nippul hanimsa
betoch chamishim
ama, harei hu shel ba'al hashovach.
So there's a dovecote, some guy's walking by and he finds this
little baby pigeon on the ground, so we say it belongs to
the שובך shovach that's within fifty אמות. ammot. חוץ מחמישים אמה הרי
הוא של מוצאו. Chutz michamishim ama, harei hu shel motza'o.
But more than fifty אמות ammot away, we say it belongs, this
is like one of the best גמרות, Gemaras, you'll see. In
the גמרא Gemara on this page, it's like one of the, for
all ישיבה בחורים yeshiva bachurim and anybody who's ever learned גמרא, Gemara,
it's exciting.
So get ready. Get ready.
So the bird, if you find it within fifty אמה, ama, then
it belongs to the owner of the dovecote. If you find it
outside of fifty אמה, ama, it belongs to the guy who finds
it. נמצא בין שתי שובכות קרוב לזה שלו קרוב לזה שלו. Nimsa
bein shtei shovcha'ot, karov lazeh shelo, karov lazeh shelo.
Let's say you find it in between two different dovecotes,
and presumably these dovecotes are built within a, there's like a Venn
diagram, there's an overlapping space where it could be within fifty אמה
ama of two different
dovecotes. So how do we know whose? So we say, oh, whichever
one it's closer to, that's the one it presumably came from.
And let's say מחצה על מחצה, mechtzah al mechtzah, let's say it's
like smack in the middle. We say שניהם יחלוקו. shneihem yachloku. So
this is not like a presumably this is not a שלמה המלך
Shlomo Hamelech cut it down the גוזל, gozal, it's like one person
compensates, I guess half the price or they take turns, however they
want to split it up, they'll figure that out.
What, I don't want to get into this, but maybe Rabbi Linzer,
you could ask Rabbi Linzer about this tomorrow.
It's very interesting that this גמרא Gemara seems to go against everything
in בבא מציעא, Bava Metzia, where it's like what do you do
when you find a lost object? You have to declare it and
get סימנים simanim for it, etc. And here it's like you find
this lost animal and like already there's already like these like inherent
claims on it about how close it is to the שובך. shovach.
Or if two people, right, in מציעא Metzia if two people are
making claims about an animal or about a lost object, you have
to like figure it out and figure out who's brought the סימנים
simanim and who's the real owner. And here we just say oh
they split it. That seems kind of odd.
But what do we know the cow, right? But why isn't it
just like
שנים אוחזין?
shnayim ochazim?
Because שנים אוחזין shnayim ochazim presumably one of them owns it. Here
this is like a lost object.
שנים אוחזין. shnayim ochazim. I mean it's at the מציעא metzia the
assumption is that to all appearances this is a wild bird. But
if it's close enough to a שובך. shovach.
Right, there's no wild טלית. tallis.
Somebody, we're not dealing with
סימנים, simanim, and you don't add, you know, we don't say with
שנים אוחזין בטלית, shnayim ochazim betallis, we don't say that they split
it. We don't say that they have to do the...
The סימנים simanim that it's near their dovecote.
You're saying they already have a claim.
שנים אוחזין בטלית shnayim ochazim betallis is they're holding it,
right?
Yeah, so but
here too they...
But those guys haven't, they haven't brought any claim. All I've done
is find this dove.
But like the cow, the lost
cow. Certain things, whatever, it won't be lost if it's in the
pasture.
It's grazing, it belongs to somebody. It will be lost if it's
whatever, running on the freeway. Right.
But I think right within fifty אמה ama of a שובך shovach
this could just be on the street though.
Right, but it wouldn't be considered completely lost
if it's within fifty אמה ama of a
שובך. shovach. You're saying so the distinction here is is this a
lost object and a special kind of lost object?
Or you mean you find it and then you have to go
put it back in the שובך? shovach? No.
I or you bring it to the owner and be like, hey
is this your birdy?
Bring it to the owner. Yeah, but you just know who it
belongs to.
Right. So but the other option we're saying is that maybe it's
not even considered a lost object in the first place and the
like general rules of מציעא Metzia don't even apply here because since
it's within the fifty אמה ama of the שובך shovach we're like
that's not, that's not a lost object at all.
It's just a bird that hasn't flown that far yet.
All right, I want to get to the exciting part. So.
אמר רבי חנינא. Amar Rabbi Chanina. Yeah, but I'm sure Rabbi Linzer
could talk to you like a forty-five minute שיעור shiur tomorrow morning
about whether it's מציעא metzia or not a מציעא metzia and the
נפקא מינות nafka minas about that. אמר רבי חנינא. Amar Rabbi Chanina.
רוב וקרוב הולכין אחר הרוב. rov vekarov holchin achar harov. So רבי
חנינא Rabbi Chanina is like, wait, hold on, this whole משנה, mishna,
the operating principle seems to be which דוכנא duchna is it closer
to? But don't we have this other idea that if you have
a situation of רוב rov and קרוב, karov, you always follow the
רוב? rov? What does that mean? There's two things רש"י Rashi explains,
there's two things from the תורה Torah about ways, two ways of
determining in a situation where there's an unknown who what the owner
is or where it came from. So one is the idea of
אחרי רבים להטות acharei rabim lehatot and that when you have a
רוב rov situation we go by the רוב. rov. So theoretically if
you had two דוכנאs, duchna you would go by the one with
the has more chicks. It's more likely that this chick came from
the דוכנא duchna that has five thousand doves than it came from
the דוכנא duchna of the guy who owns ten five doves. Exactly.
What do you mean קרוב? karov? And the other idea by קרוב
karov is we saw by עגלה ערופה, Egla Arufa, if a מת
mes is found, we go by the closest whichever city it's closest
to. רוב וקרוב הולכין
אחר הרוב, rov vekarov holchin achar harov, אף על גב דרוב דאורייתא
וקרוב דאורייתא אפילו הכי רוב עדיף. af al gav derov d'Oraita vekarov
d'Oraita afilu hachi rov adif.
Nonetheless, even though they're both דאורייתא d'Oraita concepts, we say that רובא
roba is preferable. מתיבי
רבי
זירא: Metivei Rabbi Zeira: והיה העיר הקרובה אל החלל. Vehaya hair hakerova
el hechalal. Wait, but the whole what about עגלה ערופה Egla Arufa
situation? We don't say find the nearest big city, we say go
to the closest city. אף על גב דאיכא אחריתי דנפישא מינה. Af
al gav de'ika achrita denefisha minah.
And we say any this seems to imply even though there are
other cities that are even bigger than it, we still go by
the closest city. And we say no, בדליכא, bidleika, it's actually a
situation where there's not there's no
other. וליזיל בתר רובא דעלמא, Velizul batar roba d'alma, then just go
find the biggest city in the world. Right? Where where like if
you find a dead person anywhere in America, what city is he
most likely from? New York. Right? Because
Mumbai.
Or in America, I'll say in America. I was giving a joke.
Yeah. בתר רובא דעלמא, Batar roba d'alma, right? Right.
Is Mumbai the biggest city? אף על גב דאיכא אחריתי דנפישא מינה.
Af al gav de'ika achrita
denefisha minah.
וליזיל בתר רובא דעלמא, Velizul batar roba d'alma, so like let's just
take into account the whole world. Say no, ביושבת בין ההרים. beyoshevet
bein heharim. No, we're dealing with a case of this is within
the context in like the mountain ranges. You're in some like isolated
area. You're well not quite rural,
mountainous, I'm thinking of like these little small towns in the Alps
that like there's no town for miles. Like if you find a
person, they're dead, the murderer most likely came from one of your
seventy friends who lives in the town.
Because the גמרא Gemara always does this with the משנה, mishna, right?
It's like saying, okay, the משנה mishna was talking about, but here
saying the whole, if I understand this right, the whole idea of
עגלה ערופה Egla Arufa and how you determine which city is, we're
only the תורה's Torah only talking about
cases like really isolated towns, yeah. I find it I find it
very unlikely I find it I'm very curious about other סוגיות sugyas
about עגלה ערופה Egla Arufa because this seems like a limitation or
qualification that would almost take you out, make it it would it
would change the whole our whole concept of עגלה ערופה Egla Arufa
like away from the תורה. Torah. So like it seems unlikely to
me this feels like a theoretical conversation but
right the claim if you just walked away this the only גמרא
Gemara you learned about עגלה ערופה Egla Arufa you would say like
oh the whole thing about finding the closest city that's only if
you have these like two cities in this isolated hill area then
go by the closest.
But otherwise you should always just go by the nearest big city
or the biggest city in the world, I don't know. They're writing
in בבל, Bavel, not the Alps.
Like
although there may have been small hill there's mountains in Iraq, right?
Isn't there mountains in
Iraq? There's like that's where the terrorists live. So תנן: Tnan: ניפול
הנמצא בתוך חמישים אמה הרי הוא של בעל השובך.
Nipul hanimtza betoch chamishim ama
harei hu shel ba'al hashovach.
So this seems to be in a directly parallel situation to the
עגלה ערופה Egla Arufa case. We say that you go by the
closest שובך. shovach. אף על גב דאיכא אחריתי דנפישא מיניה. Af al
gav de'ika achrita denefisha mineih.
Oh and it seems to be even though there's going to be
other דוכנאs duchna that are much bigger than it. אי הכי אימא
בדליכא I hachi eima bidleika there is not these are two equal
sized two equal sized דוכנאs. duchna אי הכי אימא סיפא: I hachi
eima seifa: חוץ מחמישים אמה הרי הוא של מוצאו. Chutz michamishim ama
harei hu shel motzo. ואי בדליכא ve'i bidleika
and if we're dealing in a situation where
there isn't a huge one,
ודאי מיניה הוא נפל. vadai mineih hu nafal.
So I don't understand. If you're going to tell me that we're
dealing with a situation where this is the only דוכנא duchna and
therefore it clearly belongs to that one, how does that help us?
The גמרא Gemara seems to say that if it's within greater than
חמישים אמה, chamishim ama, you could just keep it yourself. So why
wouldn't you just bring it there? Clearly it came from that דוכנא.
duchna.
It seems to be a little bit of a wild assuming
ייאוש ye'ush
yeah also good question. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
הכא במאי עסקינן. Hacha bemai askinan. מדדי. medadei.
No, this little גוזל, gozal, this little chick can't fly yet. All
it can do is waddle. All it can do is take these
like little steps, מדדה. medade. So דאמר רב עוקבא בר חמא כל
המדדה אין מדדה יותר מחמישים d'amar Rav Ukva Bar Chama kol hamedadeh
ein medadeh yoter mechamishim מחמישים אמה. mechamishim amah.
So we have this idea that chicks, they get to walk up
to fifty אמה. amah. That's as far as they can walk; chicks
can't walk farther than fifty אמה, amah, that's that's as far as
they can waddle. So then, here comes the famous case, בעי רבי
ירמיה. ba'i Rabbi Yirmiya. So Rabbi Yirmiya—so
that's just to be clear from the משנה, Mishnah, if the chick
walks fifty אמה, amah, less than fifty אמה amah it belongs to
that שובך, shovach, if it's more than fifty אמה amah then we
assume it didn't come from that שובך shovach because it can only
walk fifty אמה amah and therefore it belongs to the guy who
finds it. So בעי רבי ירמיה ba'i Rabbi Yirmiya says: רגלו אחת
בתוך חמישים אמה ורגלו אחת חוץ מחמישים אמה מהו. raglo achat betoch
chamishim amah veraglo achat chutz mechamishim amah mahu. So then Rabbi Yirmiya
comes along and says, wait, what if the chick has one foot
on one side of the fifty אמה amah line and the other
foot on the other side of the fifty אמה amah line? So
then who, does it belong to the dovecote or does it belong
to the guy who finds it? So what do they answer?
Anyone gonna guess? Split it. Give it.
אפקוה לרבי ירמיה מבי מדרשא. afkuh l'Rabbi Yirmiya mibei midrashah. Rabbi Yirmiya,
get out of the בית מדרש. beit midrash. That's a terrible question.
Don't ask קושיות, kashyas, right? So
what's the problem with that?
Yeah, A: the
גמרא Gemara is full of questions like that. B: תוספות Tosafot brings
up our משנה Mishnah literally just asked the question, what if you
find it exactly in between two different dovecotes? Like what do you
mean, like what do you mean you're asking—what do you mean?
The only way it can be directly between two
is it's literally the case where you have one foot on one
side and one foot on the other side. So the other, תוספות
Tosafot said,
what if there—if there—they're placed in between, they go fifty one direction,
they overlap.
Right, so you're saying like the Venn diagram thing. Yeah, that's very
serious. But so תוספות Tosafot says that actually it's not the question-asking
that bothered them. What bothered them was that we had this statement
of
they can't walk,
yeah, we had this statement of רב עוקבא Rav Ukva where he
was like, chicks, חז"ל Chazal hold that chicks can only walk fifty
אמה. amah. And here רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiya was implying that it
could actually walk even a step past fifty אמה. amah.
And he's
questioning sort of the science, the—the facts of the חכמים, Chachamim, yeah,
he's thinking too much for himself. He's saying like, wait, maybe chicks
can walk fifty אמה amah plus a half a—a half step. A
half step, a half chick step, which is like three—is like an
inch, right? So don't tell me it's exactly fifty אמה. amah.
Actually רש"י, Rashi, doesn't רש"י Rashi mean שהיה מטריח עליהם? shehayah matriach
aleihem?
Like he was just being annoying.
Making them think too hard.
Yeah, I
see.
They just didn't want to think anymore about it.
Yeah, they were just like we're not dealing with the doves like
we're moving on to the next topic, which is more doves.
Doves was a child
of Olympic dovers.
Yeah, right. Rabbi Yirmiya's like, I know all about doves and maybe
he was just like—like yeah, Rabbi Yirmiya's the dove guy. But רבי
ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiya is gonna show up in בבא בתרא Bava Batra
a few times. He's gonna ask some more questions that they're gonna
kick him out again. So it seems like pretty regular that רבי
ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiya would ask these questions that would annoy the other
people either because of the nature of the question or because they
found him maybe he was like too challenging. Maybe they're like, we're
trying to give a חקירה chakirah here about how dovecotes work and
עגלה ערופה, eglah arufah, or there's like some big deep idea here
about humans and doves and when doves fly, when humans go, and
murdering and קרוב karov and רוב. rov. And he's like, yeah, but
what if, what if the footstep is on one half of the
line and the other half of the line? Like dude,
like that's not—we're learning real תורה Torah here. Exactly.
We're—we're with big ideas and you just want to understand the situation.
Exactly.
Clearly
Rabbi Job's biases are shining through here about what he thinks of
this question. We have one minute. תא שמע. ta shema.
So now we're gonna put this to rest. נמצא בין שני שובכות
קרוב לזה שלו וקרוב לזה שלו ואף על גב דחד מינייהו נפיש
מחבריה. nimtza bein shenei shovachot karov lazeh shelo vekarov lazeh shelo veaf
al gav dechad mineihu nafish mechavreih.
And even though one of them is bigger than the other. So
like don't—we're not gonna do the רוב rov thing, we go by
קרוב. karov. הכא במאי עסקינן ששניהם שווים. hacha bemai askinan sheshneihem shavin.
Oh, so actually we do care about רוב rov and what's going
on, is there's two dovecotes of equal size. Michal and I both
have dovecotes, we each have a hundred doves in each of our
dovecote, then we go by what's closest. וליזיל
בתר רובא.
velizil batar
rova. Well let's go by the רוב rov of the whole world
like we said before. So הכא במאי עסקינן בשביל של כרמים דאי
איתא דמעלמא אתי במדדי לא מצי אתי דכל דמדדי והדר חזי לקיניה
מדדי ואי לא לא מדדי.
hacha bemai askinan beshvil shel kramim de'i ita de'mealma ati bimdadei lo
matzi ati dechol dimdadei
vehadar chazi lekeineih midadei ve'i lo lo midadei.
So it says oh, what are we dealing with? We're dealing with
a situation of you have
a vineyard. is waddling in the
in the
path and I just love the image of this גמרא *Gemara* like
you have these like little baby chicks waddling up the path in
these vineyards and we say that like it's going to we know
it's coming from one of these two vineyards so one of these
two dovecoats whichever one is closest to that's going to be the
operating principle and not about which one is greater. נקודת מחלוקת
*nekudat machloket*. Yeah.